<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="gamedev_unstable_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright 2017 © Red Hat, Inc.

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person
    obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation files
    (the "Software"), to deal in the Software without restriction,
    including without limitation the rights to use, copy, modify, merge,
    publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies of the Software,
    and to permit persons to whom the Software is furnished to do so,
    subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the
    next paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial
    portions of the Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND,
    EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF
    MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND
    NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS
    BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN
    ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF OR IN
    CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE
    SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="Wayland protocol for access to gaming devices">
    This description provides a high-level overview of the interfaces
    in this protocol. For details, see the protocol specification.

    Contemporary gaming devices are varied and usually do not interact with
    the windowing system. In many cases, a client requires direct access to
    the device to access or interpret device-specific functionality.

    This interface provides the ability for a compositor to pass a file
    descriptor to the client. The compositor may restrict the type of device
    designated as gaming device and it may restrict specific events from
    being sent to the client (e.g. by masking the Home button on a gamepad).
    Otherwise, a client should treat the device as if opened manually.

    Multiple gaming devices may exists and assigned to different seats. The
    top-level object of this protocol is a wp_gamedev_manager. A client may
    request a wp_gamedev_seat for each seat. Actual devices are assigned to
    this wp_gamedev_seat.

    Once a compositor deems a device to be focused on the client or on a
    client's surface it sends a wp_gamedev.focus_in event with a file
    descriptor for this device. A compositor may arbitrarily revoke access
    to the device by sending a wp_gamdev.focus_out. Additionally, a
    compositor may invoke system functionality to restrict access to the
    file descriptor, e.g. by using EVIOCMUTE on an evdev fd.

    Otherwise, a client should treat the file descriptor as direct access to
    the device for the duration of it having access.
  </description>

  <interface name="zwp_gamedev_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="controller object for gaming devices">
      An object that provides access to the gaming devices available on this
      system. All gaming devices are associated with a seat, to get access
      to the actual devices, use wp_gamedev_manager.get_gamedev_seat.
    </description>

    <request name="get_gamedev_seat">
      <description summary="get the gaming device seat">
	Get the wp_gamedev_seat object for the given seat. This object
	provides access to all gaming devices in this seat.
      </description>
      <arg name="gamedev_seat" type="new_id" interface="zwp_gamedev_seat_v1"/>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat" summary="The wl_seat object to retrieve the gaming devices for" />
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="release the memory for the gamedev manager object">
	Destroy the wp_gamedev_manager object. Objects created from this
	object are unaffected and should be destroyed separately.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zwp_gamedev_seat_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="controller object for gaming devices of a seat">
      An object that provides access to the gaming devices available on this
      seat. After binding to this interface, the compositor sends a set of
      wp_gamedev_seat.gamedev_added.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="release the memory for the gamedev seat object">
	Destroy the wp_gamedev_seat object. Objects created from this
	object are unaffected and should be destroyed separately.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="gamedev_added">
      <description summary="new device notification">
	This event is sent whenever a new gaming device becomes available on
	this seat. This event only provides the object id of the devices, any
	static information about the gaming device (device name, vid/pid,
	etc.) is sent through the wp_gamedev interface.

	Which devices are gaming devices is a decision made by the compositor,
	the protocol makes no guarantee that any specific device becomes available
	as gaming device to a client.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zwp_gamedev_v1" summary="the newly added gaming device"/>
    </event>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zwp_gamedev_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="gaming device">
      The wp_gamedev interface represents one gaming device. Access to a
      gaming device may be restricted based on compositor policy.

      A gaming device has a number of static characteristics, e.g. device
      name and pid/vid. These capabilities are sent in an event sequence
      after the wp_gamedev_seat.gamedev_added event. This initial event
      sequence is terminated by a wp_gamedev.done event. This sequence is
      sent only once and always before the first wp_gamedev.focus_in event.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the gamedev object">
	This destroys the client's resource for this gamedev object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="name">
      <description summary="gaming device name">
	This event is sent in the initial burst of events before the
	wp_gamedev.done event.

	This event is optional, if the required information is not available
	for this device the event is omitted.
      </description>
      <arg name="name" type="string" summary="the device name"/>
    </event>

    <event name="usb_id">
      <description summary="gaming device USB vendor/product id">
	This event is sent in the initial burst of events before the
	wp_gamedev.done event.

	This event is optional, if the required information is not available
	for this device the event is omitted.
      </description>
      <arg name="vid" type="uint" summary="USB vendor id"/>
      <arg name="pid" type="uint" summary="USB product id"/>
    </event>

    <event name="property">
      <description summary="gaming device capability notification">
	This event is sent to notify the client of a custom property that
	applies to this device. The property is a standard key/value store
	in UTF-8 format, interpretation of both strings is left to the
	client. The wayland protocol makes no guarantees about the content
	of each string beyond its text encoding.

	Compositors and clients need to agree on a dictionary of properties.
	This dictionary is out of the scope of this protocol.
      </description>
      <arg name="property" type="string" summary="A UTF-8 encoded property name"/>
      <arg name="value" type="string" summary="A UTF-8 encoded property value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="done">
      <description summary="gaming device description events sequence complete">
	This event is sent immediately to signal the end of the initial
	burst of descriptive events. A client may consider the static
	description of the device to be complete and finalize
	initialization of the device.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="removed">
      <description summary="gaming device removed event">
	Sent when the device has been removed from the system.

	If the client currently has the device focus and the device is
	removed, a wp_gamedev.focus_out event is sent before a removed
	event. See wp_gamedev.focus_in for more details.

	When this event is received, the client must wp_gamedev.destroy
	the object.
      </description>
    </event>

    <enum name="fd_type">
      <description summary="Gaming device file descriptor types">
	This enum specifies the format of the file descriptor passed to
	clients with the wp_gamedev.focus_in event.
      </description>
      <entry name="evdev" value="0" summary="An evdev file descriptor" />
    </enum>

    <event name="focus_in">
      <description summary="gaming device focus in event">
	Notification that this client now has the focus and/or access to
	this gaming device. The decision what consitutes focus left to the
	compositor. For example, a compositor may tie joystick focus to the
	wl_pointer focus of this seat. The protocol does not guarantee that
	any specific client ever receives the focus for a gaming device.

	The client is passed a file descriptor with access to this gaming
	device. This file descriptor is valid until a subsequent
	wp_gamedev.focus_out event. Upon wp_gamedev.focus_out, the
	compositor may revoke the fd and further operations will fail.

	However, due to potential race conditions a client must be able to
	handle errors as if it opened the fd itself. No guarantee is
	given that the wp_gamedev.focus_out event or wp_gamedev.removed
	event are sent before the client encounters an error on the file
	descriptor.

	A compositor guarantees that the underlying device does not change
	until a wp_gamedev.removed event. In other words, a client only
	needs to query capabilities once on the first focus_in, regardless
	of how many focus_out events follow.

	If applicable, this event contains the surface that has the focus.
	In some cases, the focus may not be tied to a specific client surface
	but is given to the client on a global basis. In that case, the surface
	is null.

	The protocol guarantees that focus_in and focus_out always come in
	pairs. If the client currently has the focus and the device is
	removed, a focus_out event is sent to the client before the
	wp_gamedev.removed event.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="fd" type="fd" summary="file descriptor to the gaming device"/>
      <arg name="fd_type" type="uint" enum="fd_type" summary="fd type" />
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface" summary="The current surface that has the gaming device's focus" allow-null="true"/>
    </event>

    <event name="focus_out">
      <description summary="gaming device focus out event">
	Notification that this client no longer has focus and/or access to
	this gaming device. Further reads from this device's file descriptor
	will fail. The client must close(2) the file descriptor received in
	the wp_gamedev.focus_in event.

	This event does not mean the device was removed, merely that the
	device is focused elsewhere. For device removal, see
	wp_gamedev.removed.

	See wp_gamedev.focus_in for more details.
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>


